# David Poirier-Quinot

# Audio VR Researcher

258B Rue de Paris 93100 Montreuil (+33)6 24 94 03 38 davipoir@gmail.com https://pyrapple.github.io

#### EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

I'm a researcher, presently focused on sound spatialisation, perception, and room acoustics simulation for virtual and augmented realities. I studied these fields along with signal processing and computer sciences at d'Alembert Institute, Imperial College London, IRCAM, LIMSI, and ETIS labs.

With a background in Mathematics, Physics and Chemistry, I obtained a Master's degree in signal processing and telecommunications from the ENSEA graduate school of Electrical Engineering (France) in 2011, and received a Ph.D. degree in acoustics, signal processing, and computer science from Sorbonne University (Paris VI, France) in May 2015.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD in Computer Science, Acoustics, and Virtual Reality

2012 - 2015

CNRS (LIMSI, ETIS), Airbus Defense & Space, Paris

Signal Processing, DOA estimation (EM), Acoustics, Ergonomics, VR, Sound Design

#### Master Degree in Network and Telecom Engineering

2008 - 2011

ENSEA graduate school of electrical eng. and computer science, Cergy Network, Telecommunications, Signal Processing, Analog Electronics

#### **SKILLS**

Language French (native), English (fluent), Spanish (basic)

Python, C++, C#, Javascript, Matlab, HTML, CSS, Lisp, Java, C, Objective-C
Software
Blender, Unity3D, Unreal Engine, Max, Juce, Pd, CATT-Acoustic, Photoshop
Others
Perceptive exp. design, data analysis, scientific writing, functionnal analysis, IP

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

Oct. 2017 - Today

d'Alembert Institute – CNRS – Sorbonne University, Paris

Binaural perception in VR applications (partnership with Facebook Reality Labs): impact of individualised binaural rendering on performance and immersion, HRTF learning.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

May 2016 – Sept. 2017

IRCAM – CNRS, Paris

Distributed spatial audio through web-based applications. Development of WebAudio spatialisation libraries (binaural, Ambisonic) for mixed realities. Design of a framework for real-time auralisation in architectural acoustics and virtual reality.

# Postdoctoral Researcher

Nov. 2015 – May 2016

Imperial College London, London

Study of the impact of room acoustics on 3D audio perception. Perceptive comparison of reverberation techniques for 3D audio. Hearing loss simulation.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

June 2015 - Oct. 2015

LIMSI - CNRS, Paris

Room acoustic simulation and 3D sound design for virtual reality.

### Postdoctoral Researcher

May 2016 - Apr. 2018

Imperial College London, London

(part-time) Design of a toolkit for binaural spatialisation. Simulation of the impact of hearing loss on sound perception. Study of the impact of Ambisonic room reverb order on auditory scene perception.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

Apr. 2015 – June 2015

Imperial College London, London

Design of a VR experiment on audio subjective perception in room acoustics.

**PhD Thesis** Feb. 2012 – Mar. 2015

Airbus Defense & Space, CNRS (LIMSI, ETIS), Paris

"Design of a radio Direction Finder for search and rescue operations". Interfacing of propagation models and virtual environments for ecological assessment of Direction Finder designs performance.

# Research Engineer

Sept. 2011 – Jan. 2012

LIMSI – CNRS, Paris

Implementation and deployment of sound spatialisation systems (Ambisonic, Binaural, WFS). Development of a scene graph editor for VR architectures.

#### MAIN PROJECTS

Anaglyph 2018

High-definition binaural spatialisation engine. http://anaglyph.dalembert.upmc.fr

Cloud Theatre 2018

Virtual performance in the Athénée Theatre, Paris. Visual rendering, actor holograms, room acoustic and voice directivity simulation. https://pyrapple.github.io/pages/cloud-theatre.html

EVERTims 2017

Open source framework for real-time auralisation in architectural acoustics and virtual reality. http://evertims.github.io

Ghost Orchestra 2016

Virtual recreation of a concert in Notre-Dame de Paris Cathedral. Room acoustic simulation and visual rendering. https://groupeaa.limsi.fr/projets:ghostorch

BlenderVR 2015

Scene graph editor for VR architectures. Adaptation of the Blender Game Engine to support CAVE, VideoWall, HMD, and external rendering modality engines. https://blendervr.limsi.fr

- D. Poirier-Quinot, G. Parseihian, and B. F. G. Katz, "Comparative study on the effect of Parameter Mapping Sonification on perceived instabilities, efficiency, and accuracy in real-time interactive exploration of noisy data streams," *Displays*, vol. 47, pp. 2 11, 2017
- L. Picinali, A. Wallin, Y. Levtov, and D. Poirier-Quinot, "Comparative perceptual evaluation between different methods for implementing reverberation in a binaural context," in *AES Convention* 142, (Berlin, Germany), May 2017
- A. Politis and D. Poirier-Quinot, "JSAmbisonics: A Web Audio library for interactive spatial sound processing on the web," in *Interactive Audio Systems Symposium*, York, UK, pp. 1–8, 09 2016
- D. Poirier-Quinot, B. Matuszewski, N. Schnell, and O. Warusfel, "Nü Soundworks: using spectators smartphones as a distributed network of speakers and sensors during live performances," in *Web Audio Conference*, (London, United Kingdom), Aug. 2017
- D. Poirier-Quinot, B. F. Katz, and M. Noisternig, "EVERTims: Open source framework for real-time auralization in architectural acoustics and virtual reality," in 20th International Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-17), (Edinburgh, United Kingdom), Sept. 2017
- B. F. G. Katz, B. N. J. Postma, D. Poirier-Quinot, and J. Meyer, "Experience with a virtual reality auralization of Notre-Dame Cathedral," in *Acoustical Society of America*, vol. 141, (Boston, United States), pp. 3454 3454, June 2017
- D. Thery, D. Poirier-Quinot, B. N. Postma, and B. F. G. Katz, "Impact of the Visual Rendering System on Subjective Auralization Assessment in VR," in *Virtual Reality and Augmented Reality* (J. Barbic, M. D'Cruz, M. Latoschik, M. Slater, and P. Bourdot, eds.), no. 10700 (EuroVR 2017) in Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 105–118, Springer, 2017

See https://pyrapple.github.io/pages/publications.html for an exhaustive list of publications.